Hey, I'm going on a tour of the United
Kingdom. If you've ever been interested
in that big question of God's existence
or try to make sense of religion in the
21st century or consciousness or
anything philosophical, then join me on
stage as I try to work out some of these
topics with you. I'll be in conversation
with a good friend, but also bring
questions because there will be an
extensive Q&A and maybe even an
opportunity to hear and rate some of
your philosophical hot takes. The tour
dates are on screen. The link to buy
tickets is in the description and I hope
to see you there. I think that the
sort of
dogged pursuit of political power and
the consolidation of political power
especially in the United States by
Christians is one of the biggest
betrayals of the teachings of Jesus.
And I think that it has been
disillusioning to a lot of Christians.
Interestingly, my entire deconstruction
happened outside of that and kind of now
I was a conservative Christian. I voted
Republican because of abortion probably
alone. Um,
but the political landscape has changed
a lot and at this point
the
kind of the the embrace of the pursuit
of political power and talking about it
and how it's spreading to more and more
Christians.
I feel like this is a new level. I don't
think this is something that I
experienced, you know, 15 years ago when
I was deconstructing.
Um, so I want to talk a little bit about
what Jesus has to say about this or, you
know, what the Bible has to say about
this and then we can kind of talk about
why why I think this is such a problem.
>> Um,
let's start
in when Jesus is before Pilate, right?
So, this is just kind of setting the
stage. You've got Jesus before Pilate in
John 18.
>> Mhm.
>> And um he essentially says, you know, P
well Pilate is basically asking him
like, you know, well, let me just say
it. Let me just read it. So Pilate
entered his headquarters again and
called Jesus and said to him, "Are you
the king of the Jews?" Jesus answered,
"Do you say this of your own accord or
did others say it to you about me?"
Pilate answered, "Am I a Jew? Your own
nation and the chief priests have
delivered you over to me. What have you
done?" And Jesus answered, "My kingdom
is not of this world. If my kingdom were
of this world, my servants would have
been fighting that I might not be
delivered over to the Jews. But my
kingdom is not from this world."
>> So again, here we are. Jesus is having
this this
moment where he is been taken in and
he's being taken in by the political
forces that existed at that time where
they were kind of executing the will of
God to literally execute him. And what
did he do? He said, he took that
opportunity to say, "My kingdom, this is
not about th this worldly kingdom that
you're talking about. My kingdom is not
of this world."
>> And if it were, my servants would be
fighting.
>> They'd be doing something about it right
now. They would be in here doing
something about it. The reason that they
are not resistant, in fact, earlier when
Peter cuts off the ear,
>> he's like, "No." He puts it back on, you
know? He's like, "No, no, that's not
what we're doing. We're not fighting.
We're not here to fight."
>> You don't get that anywhere from Jesus,
right? Well, you get that a little bit
from Israel, which I think is one of the
reasons that that I think Christian
nationalism is a little bit confused
about trying to be basically be the
nation of Israel today. It's like it's a
little complicated, but let's just talk
about Jesus
>> and the imagery there of Trump with
literally a a broken ear shouting fight.
>> Yeah, exactly. Exactly. [laughter]
>> Quite stark contrast,
>> right? But it gets I think it gets even
more explicit. So this is the famous
passage where the Pharisees try to trap
Jesus in the question about taxes.
>> Um
so uh they had been giving him a number
of different challenges to to catch him,
right? And so uh we we'll just kind of
cover this because I can remember the
details. So you know they had this the
Pharisees have this idea to come and ask
Jesus if they should pay taxes to
Caesar. And the reason that they thought
that this was a trap is because if he's
supposed to be the Messiah, at least as
they understand it, he's supposed to be
the one delivering them from this Roman
rule. So if he's like saying, "Yeah, we
should give money to our oppressors,"
not a very good Messiah according to
their perspective. And if he says,
>> "Yeah, no, we shouldn't pay taxes." Then
then they report him and get him
delivered to the Romans.
>> Right? So this was like a nice setup.
And when they do this, they say, "Should
we pay taxes?" to Caesar. He's like,
"Grab me a daenerius. Grab me a coin."
And then he takes it and he says, "Who
is this on the coin?" And they say,
"Caesar." And he says, "Render to Caesar
what is Caesars's and to God what is
God's." Why is this so important? And
why is this so relevant to the current
situation? Notice he didn't say anything
like, "See this coin?
It should say in Yahweh we trust on it."
M
>> that's the battle that we should be
fighting. We should be fighting to get
the kingdom that is oppressing us or the
kingdom of this world to represent
God. He's basically saying this is
irrelevant to my mission. Yeah. Pay
taxes to Caesar. That's a completely
different thing. This embrace of
political power and thinking that that
is the answer. That's how we bring about
the kingdom of God. It is a complete
misunderstanding of what Jesus was
talking about.
>> Um, and I do think it's wild because you
the whole in you know you know the in
God we trust on the American money like
I that was it's a pretty recent
innovation. I can't remember
>> cold war thing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I I think I I can't
remember exactly when it
>> Oh, [laughter]
look. That's water. [laughter]
>> Yeah. All right. All right.
>> Right on to the Bible. You know, I only
did that to make you feel welcome.
[laughter]
Okay, where were we?
>> Everything's cleaned up. You know, my
Bible's a little bit wet. No worse.
Okay.
>> Holy holy water now on the table.
>> So, I think that this this last passage
is the one that is the most um
informative about this and you've talked
about it a moment ago,
>> the temptation of Jesus. And of course,
he's out there in the the wilderness for
40 days.
>> And so, there's the three temptations
from the devil. The first being, you
know, eat some turns these stones into
bread. Uh the next one being throw
yourself off of this and the angels will
save you. And then the third one being
going up to the top of the mountain
saying look at all the kingdoms of the
world. I will give you all of this if
you will just bow down and worship me.
And of course Jesus says be gone Satan.
You know listen what does it say exactly
in the ESV? He says
>> worship God and serve him alone.
>> Yeah. Be gone, Satan, for it is written,
you shall worship the Lord your God and
serve, and only him so shall you serve.
Again, it's the
>> And interestingly, it's not that's not
actually written. There's no there Jesus
is like slightly rewarding the passage
he's trying the in in the Old Testament,
the passage is something like um it's
something like
fear. I think it's fear God and serve
him only or something like that. It
doesn't use the word worship, which is
obviously it's, you know, Greek and
Hebrew, but he's not actually quoting it
quite correctly there, which is
interesting. Um,
>> yeah, it is.
>> Side note, footnote.
>> Yeah, footnote.
>> Continue.
>> So,
this to me, this is pretty wild
considering the state of the current
American church. M
>> um
because there's a lot going on here
theologically of course, but the one
opportunity that
Jesus
has to make a commentary about embracing
political power over the kingdom or the
kingdoms of this world
is presented as a temptation of Satan.
[laughter]
This is presented as a temptation of
Satan to fall for this. We've got to be
we've got to be in control of the the
the kingdoms of the world. Does Jesus
say, "Well, okay, maybe you're in charge
right now, but you just wait until a few
of my followers are are are in
government, or you you wait until we're
in charge." Again, he says, "It's not
about that. We are operating on a
different plane." And it just blows my
mind that we've gotten to this place
where this seems to be the way that the
kingdom of God is going to be
established is by infiltrating and
taking over the government. And I'm not
just saying that it's not a good idea
from a Christian perspective. I'm saying
it is forbidden.
>> I'm saying that it is explicitly called
out as something that will take you away
from actually doing the work of God.
>> And I think it's interesting. I think
it's worth noting that the more that
Christians have embraced this pursuit of
political power, the more they have
embraced political leadership that looks
a lot less like Jesus and a lot more
like the devil himself.
[laughter]
>> Is that not crazy?
>> Yeah, I think it's I think it's true,
but it's also it's also maybe it's a bit
easy to say like you know that if you
pursue political power, you begin sort
of betray principles. And some people
will listen to this and I think there
are two things which people will say in
response to this. One thing is they'll
say okay but if you look at the Old
Testament you know God is constantly
installing literal political kings.
There are at least some contexts in
which God thought that it was necessary
to have you know his his rulers on
earth. I think I know what I would say
in response to that. I wonder what you
would say. And the second thing is then
okay I'm a I'm a Christian. I'm sat at
home. I'm listening to this. Don't clip
that either. Um, and I would like to
know what to do then because I care
about what's happening in my country and
I I want to vote for somebody who shares
my values, but am I supposed to am I
supposed to look at anybody who says I'm
a Christian and I'm running on Christian
motivations and say no no no I'm not
going to vote for you because you know
that can't be true. Whereas I feel like
I want someone who's Christian to you
know run my like what can they actually
do?
>> Those are good questions to to answer
the first. I think that the kingdom of
Israel of which was, you know, sort of
preparing the way for the Messiah that
he comes out of, that's a different
thing. That's not America.
>> That's, you know, that that doesn't
apply to these kingdoms. That's a that's
a different thing. I I don't think
there's a theological justification for
applying principles of the way that God
was establishing and upholding his
nation for his people
>> and then trying to apply that even to
modern day Israel or definitely to any
other kingdom. That just feels like that
you can't you that dog won't hunt as
they say.
>> To the extent that we can make sense of
God having like a chosen people and a
chosen nation, it seems like America
despite what they think um might not be
that. But even so, there is this please
don't revoke my visa. The problem that
the other thing is that like Jesus is
presented as this fulfillment and sort
of fulfillment of but also like in many
ways like he sort of um removes the the
need for certain kinds of Jewish
practices. So like there's this idea
that Jesus is kind of like the new
Jewish temple. You know it used to be
that you worship in this particular
place and this is where you meet God and
now it's Jesus and Jesus is everywhere
and anywhere. And a similar kind of
thing is happening here with like
authority. I mean the the Jewish kingdom
was waiting for the Messiah who would be
you know their ultimate king and when
the ultimate king comes he's not a
political leader. He is the opposite of
political leader. So I think that the
extent to which this is specifically a
problem like if somebody's listening in
other words and says okay yeah but you
know Rhett doesn't understand that you
know that in the Old Testament political
power was really important. This is just
the problem of the relationship of the
Old Testament to the New Testament.
Yeah. Because I could say the same thing
to a Christian like, well, if your Jesus
is doing this or that or that or that,
>> then what about in the Old Testament
where God's commanding this that that or
that or this thing you're supposed to do
that you're no longer supposed to do or
whatever. It's just the same problem um
revisited. As long as a Christian is
willing to say that, yeah, Jesus changed
changed the nature of God's relationship
with Earth.
>> Exactly.
>> The same things here. But okay, that's
sort of out of the way.
>> So, what does a Christian do?
>> What does a Christian do?
>> So, I think this is a I think it's a
great question. uh because I would say
the extreme application of this
perspective is abstaining from political
involvement at all and there are
denominations that do that.
>> Um and you have to respect that. Um this
is a bit of again there's so many layers
of this. There's a bit of a conundrum
considering that I don't think that any
of the people who were reading this at
the time thought that in the year 2025
the world would still be around.
>> That's right. Uh, so I don't think that
they envision 2,000 years of more
kingdoms in in in what we have here. So
we find ourselves in a situation that
maybe some of this philosophy doesn't
specifically apply because, you know,
they were selling all their stuff not
because they were communist but because
they thought Yeah. Right.
>> Yeah.
um it becomes a bit easier to say like
who cares about the government whatever
that the world is about to end which
makes it a bit complicated because for a
Christian they kind of have to interpret
this not them not believing the world is
about to end because
>> again so that so I'm going with that I'm
trying I'm just saying be I believe that
they thought that Jesus was coming back
yeah and he didn't
>> but as a Christian you do you believe
that he that he wasn't intending that
and that he knew that the world will
still still be around in 2025. What I'm
saying is that it is a temptation
because you start believing that the
only way to get what God wants is for
you to do it for him through human
means. And I think that ultimately when
you feel like the people in power
politically have to represent your
worldview, it indicates that you're
fearful that if that wasn't the case
that God couldn't do what he needed to
do. And so I think this is this is a
higher calling to a level of spirit sp
spirituality and commitment to the
kingdom that does I think that if you
follow this
wholeheartedly
I think it means that I'm not saying you
don't vote but I think that the idea
that the answer is to install Christians
into political office and that's where
your hope lies and to work very
tirelessly for that that's just it's not
biblical and I think ultimately
I don't think you can hold on to
political power
and Jesus at the same time. I think that
if you're gonna hold on to Jesus and
you're holding on to to this world,
you've kind of got to drop that pursuit
in the same way. And the crazy thing
that happens as a result of this is you
end up align like I said, you end up
aligning yourselves with people who do
not represent
um you know this the the the fruit of
the spirit that you've got people who
are living in fear. I think this is
another aspect of this is that so much
of the current political pursuit
pursuit of political power is based in
fear. You've got people all across the
United States mainlining Fox News and
the like every single night. Like, give
it to me. Give me that stuff that makes
me fearful every single night. I got to
be afraid of the brown people who are
going to take my jobs. Or, you know, I
got to be afraid of the people who are
going to come take my guns. I got to be
afraid of the trans woman who might come
into my daughter's restroom. Right? And
and so frankly, that whole thing pisses
me off because I feel like an entire
generation has been stolen from us
because you have what could be older,
wiser people who have perspective, but
yet they have been completely captivated
by fear and they tap into it every
single night. Like that pisses me off
that a generation has been stolen from
us. But what if I I just this is a
hypothetical. What if Christians in
America were not mostly known for
wanting to have political power and all
of the things that come along with that
and all the fear that that is based in
and instead they had they were cool,
calm, and collected because they trusted
that God was accomplishing his purpose
and they were busying themselves with
the work of Jesus being the hands and
feet of Jesus. Feeding the poor, caring
for the orphan, caring for the elderly,
caring for the widow.
It seems to me that they don't believe
that that would actually do anything.
That that that level of spiritual
commitment to being like, I'm going to
be about the kingdom and I'm going to
trust that God will accomplish his
accomplish his will through me in that.
I just think it's a lack of faith. I
think it kind of goes back, we come full
circle is that there's not a real faith
that God can accomplish his purpose
apart from you putting the Ten
Commandments up in every courthouse.
Really? Like you really think that
that's what's going to do it? Yeah. If
you're anything like me, then getting
the right kind of food in your diet can
be a bit of a challenge. And in times
that I've been struggling to get all of
the vitamins and minerals that I need,
it's these guys, huh that have come to
the rescue. This black edition is a
complete meal. 400 calories, 35 g of
vegan protein, 26 vitamins and minerals.
It's high protein, low sugar, and low
cost, all while saving your time as
well. I like this prepackaged edition.
This is the chocolate flavor, but it
also comes in chocolate, peanut butter,
salted caramel, iced latte, all kinds of
different flavors. So, just go to
hule.com/alexoc
okconor. And if you use the code Alex
Okconor at checkout as a new customer,
you'll also get 15% off complete
nutrition while saving your time and
your